<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/usr/share/xml/geekodoc/rng/geekodoc5-flat.rnc"
   type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-trento-user-management">
  <title>User management</title>
  <para>
    Trento provides a local permission-based user management feature with
    optional multi-factor authentication. This feature allows for segregation of
    duties in the Trento console and ensures that only authorized users with the
    right permissions can access it.
  </para>
  <para>
    User management actions are performed in the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> view
    in the left-hand side panel of the &t.web;.
  </para>
  <para>
    By default, a newly created user is granted display access rights except for
    the
    <guimenu>Users</guimenu> view. Whenever available, a user with default access can set up
    filters and pagination settings matching their preferences.
  </para>
  <para>
    Additional permissions must be added to a user profile, so that the user can
    perform the corresponding protected activities. The following permissions
    are currently available:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <constant>all:users</constant>: grants full access to user management actions under the
        <guimenu>Users</guimenu> view
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <constant>all:checks_selection</constant>: grants check selection
        capabilities for any target in the registered environment for which
        checks are available
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <constant>all:checks_execution</constant>: grants check execution
        capabilities for any target in the registered environment for which
        checks are available and have been previously selected
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <constant>all:tags</constant>: allows creation and deletion of the available tags
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <constant>cleanup:all</constant>: allows triggering housekeeping actions
        on hosts where agents heartbeat is lost and SAP or HANA instances that
        are no longer found
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <constant>all:settings</constant>: grants changing capabilities on any
        system settings under the <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> view
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <constant>all:all</constant>: grants all the permissions above
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    Using the described permissions, it is possible to create the following types of users:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title>User managers:</title>
        <para>
          users with <constant>all:users</constant> permission
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title>SAP Basis administrator with Trento display-only access:</title>
        <para>
          users with default permissions
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title>SAP Basis administrator with Trento configuration access:</title>
        <para>
          users with <constant>all:checks_selection</constant>, <constant>all:tags</constant> and
          <constant>all:settings</constant> permissions
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title>SAP Basis administrator with Trento operation access:</title>
        <para>
          users with <constant>all:check_execution</constant> and <constant>cleanup:all</constant>
          permissions.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    The default admin user created during the installation process is granted
    <constant>all:all</constant> permissions and cannot be modified or deleted.
    Use it only to create a first user manager. That is, a user with
    <constant>all:users</constant> permissions who creates all the other
    required users. Once a user with all:users permissions is created, the
    default admin user must be regarded as a fall-back user to be used only in
    case all other access to the console is lost. If the password of the default
    admin user is lost, it can be reset by updating the helm chart or the web
    component configuration, depending on which deployment method was used to
    install &t.server;.
  </para>
  <para>
    User passwords, including the default admin user password, must follow the rules below:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Password must contain at least 8 characters
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The same number or letter must not be repeated three or more times in a row (for example:
        111 or aaa)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Password must not contain four consecutive numbers or letters (for
        example: 1234, abcd or ABCD)
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    The <guimenu>Create User</guimenu> and <guimenu>Edit User</guimenu> views
    provide a built-in generation password action button that allows user
    managers to easily generate secure and compliant passwords. The user manager
    must provide the user with their password through an authorized secure
    channel.
  </para>
  <para>
    A user can reset their password in the <guimenu>Profile</guimenu> view.
    Here, they can also update their name and email address as well as activate
    multi-factor authentication using an authenticator app. Multi-factor
    authentication increases the security of a user account by requesting a
    temporary second password or code when logging in the console. User managers
    can disable multi-factor authentication for any given user that has it
    enabled. However, user managers cannot enable multi-factor authentication on
    their behalf. The default admin user cannot enable its own multi-factor
    authentication.
  </para>
  <note>
    <title>Security Tip for Multi-Factor Authentication</title>
    <para>
      Since multi-factor authentication cannot be enabled for the default admin
      user, keeping its password safe is imperative. If the default admin user's
      password is compromised, reset it immediately by updating the helm chart
      or the web component configuration, depending on which deployment method
      was used to install &t.server;.
    </para>
  </note>
  <para>
    User managers can enable and disable users. When a user logged in the
    console is disabled by a user admin, their session is terminated
    immediately.
  </para>
</section>
