<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/usr/share/xml/geekodoc/rng/geekodoc5-flat.rnc"
   type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-activity-log">
  <title>Activity Log</title>
  <para>
    &trento; collects system events and user actions in the Activity Log. It can
    be accessed from the left-hand side panel of the &trento; console.
  </para>
  <para>
    Each entry in the Activity Log includes the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A timestamp: the day and time (server time, not browser time) the system
        event or the user action occurred
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A message: type of the occurred event or user action
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The user that triggered the event or performed the action. User system
        is used for events triggered by the system itself.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    Clicking on the chevron icon in the activity log entry opens a modal window containing the activity metadata.
  </para>
  <para>
    The Activity Log allows to filter by the type of event or user action
    (commonly referred to as resource type) and by the user that triggered the
    event or performed the action. Only active users are available for
    filtering. The Activity Log also allows you to filter out entries that are
    newer and/or older than an specific date and time (server time).
  </para>
  <para>
    Once a filter has been set, click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> to filter out the
    undesired entries and <guimenu>Reset</guimenu> to remove all the filters.
  </para>
  <para>
    Entries related to user management can only be displayed by users that have
    the <constant>all:all</constant> or <constant>all:users</constant>  permissions. This includes the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Login attempts
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        User creations
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        User modifications
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        User deletions
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Profile updates
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    Entries in the Activity Log are sorted from newer to older. Click
    <guimenu>Refresh</guimenu> to update the Activity Log view with entries
    generated since they accessed the view or after the last refresh
  </para>
  <para>
    The pagination features at the bottom of the Activity Log allow you to
    specify the number of entries to display in a page, go to the next or
    previous page of the view, and jump to the last page and back to first one.
  </para>
  <para>
    The default retention time for entries in the Activity Log is one month.
    This can be changed in the Activity Log section under
    <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Changing the retention time requires the
    <constant>all:settings</constant> permissions. Entries older than the specified retention time are deleted every day at midnight (server time).
  </para>
</section>
