<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/usr/share/xml/geekodoc/rng/geekodoc5-flat.rnc"
   type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="sec-trento-manage-tags">
      <title>Managing tags</title>
      <para>
       Tags are a means to label specific objects with a purpose, location, owner, or any other
       property you like. Such objects can be hosts, clusters, databases, or SAP systems.
       Tags make it easier to distinguish and show all these different objects, making
       your lists more readable and searchable. You can use any text you like to create
       your tags except blank spaces and special characters other than + - = . , _ : and @.
      </para>
      <para>
        The following subsection shows how you can add, remove, and filter objects based on
        your tags.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="sec-trento-add-tags">
        <title>Adding tags to hosts, clusters, databases, and SAP Systems</title>
        <para>
          To add one or more tags to your objects, do the following:
        </para>
        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>
              Log in to Trento.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              In the Trento dashboard, go to the overview corresponding to the object for which you want to create tags. For example, the <guimenu>Hosts</guimenu> overview.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              In the <guimenu>Hosts</guimenu> overview, search for the host you want to add a tag to.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              In the <guimenu>Tags</guimenu> column, click the <guimenu>Add Tag</guimenu> entry.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>Enter the respective tag and finish with <keycap function="enter"/>.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              Repeat this procedure to assign as many tags as you want. It can be on the same
              or on a different host.
            </para>
          </step>
        </procedure>
        <para>
          After you have finished the above procedure, the changed host contains one or
          more tags.
        </para>
        <para>
          The same principle applies to other objects in Trento, be it <guimenu>Clusters</guimenu>,
          <guimenu>SAP Systems</guimenu>, or <guimenu>HANA Databases</guimenu>.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="sec-trento-remove-tags">
        <title>Removing tags</title>
        <para>
          If you want to remove existing tags, click the respective part in the dashboard:
        </para>
        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>
              Log in to Trento.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
<para>
In the Trento dashboard, go to the overview corresponding to the object for which you want to remove tags. For example, the <guimenu>Hosts</guimenu> overview.
</para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              In the <guimenu>Hosts</guimenu> overview, search for the host you want to remove a tag from.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              In the <guimenu>Tags</guimenu> column, click the <guimenu>×</guimenu> icon to remove
              the tag.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              Repeat this procedure to remove as many tags as you want. It can be on the same
              or on a different host.
            </para>
          </step>
        </procedure>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="sec-trento-filter-tags">
        <title>Filter by tags</title>
        <para>
          With tags, you can show only those objects you are interested in. For example, if
          you have created a <literal>drbd</literal> tag for some hosts, you can show only
          those hosts that have this <literal>drbd</literal> tag assigned.
        </para>
        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>
              In the Trento dashboard, go to the respective overview you are interested in.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              Make sure you have already assigned some tags. If not, refer to <xref linkend="sec-trento-add-tags"/>.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              In the second row, click the last drop-down list with the name <guimenu>Filter tags</guimenu>.
              The drop-down list opens and shows you all of your defined tags.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              Select the tag you want to filter from the drop-down list.
              It is possible to select more than one tag.
            </para>
          </step>
        </procedure>
        <para>
          After you have finished the above procedure, Trento shows all respective hosts that
          contain one or more of your selected tags.
        </para>
        <para>
          To remove the filter, click the <guimenu>×</guimenu> icon from the same drop-down list.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>