<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/usr/share/xml/geekodoc/rng/geekodoc5-flat.rnc"
   type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="sec-trento-what">
    <title>What is &trento;?</title>
    <para>
      &trento; is the official version of the Trento community project. It is a comprehensive monitoring solution
      consisting of two main components: the &t.server; and the &t.agent;.
      &trento; provides the following functionality and features:
    </para>
    <remark>toms 2024-04-18 (change#9): maybe a reference here about improved HANA multitenant support?</remark>
    <!--
      from https://confluence.suse.com/x/uoOyN
    -->
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A user-friendly interface for &sap; Basis administrators.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Automated discovery of &pace; clusters using SAPHanaSR classic or angi
          as well as different fencing mechanisms, including diskless SBD.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     Automated discovery of SAP systems running on ABAP or JAVA stacks and HANA databases.
        </para>
      </listitem>
          <listitem>
        <para>
     Awareness of maintenance situations in a &pace; cluster at cluster, node, or resource level.
                  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Configuration validation for &hana; Scale-Up
        Performance-optimized, &hana; Scale-out and ASCS/ERS clusters deployed
        on Azure, AWS, GCP or on-premises bare metal platforms, including KVM
        and Nutanix.
        </para>
      </listitem>
         <listitem>
        <para>Useful information about the execution of configuration checks.
        </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
        <para>Configuration checks that are unbundled from the wanda check engine.
        </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
        <para>
          Email alerting for critical events in the monitored landscape.
        </para>
      </listitem>
              <listitem>
        <para>
          Integration of saptune into the console and specific configuration checks at host and cluster levels.
        </para>
      </listitem>
              <listitem>
        <para>
          Information about relevant patches, advisories, and upgradable packages for registered hosts via integration with &suma;.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Monitoring of CPU and memory usage at the host level through basic integration with &prometheus;.
        </para>
      </listitem>
           <listitem>
        <para>
          API-based architecture to facilitate integration with other monitoring tools.
        </para>
                  </listitem>
      <listitem>
             <para>
          Rotating API key to protect communication between the &t.agent; and the &t.server;.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
             <para>
          Housekeeping capabilities.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para> The <emphasis role="strong">&t.server;</emphasis> is an
      independent, distributed system designed to run
      on a &k8s; cluster or as a regular systemd stack.
      The &t.server; provides a Web front-end for user interaction. The &t.server; consists of the following components:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The web component that acts as a control plane responsible for internal and external communications as well as rendering the UI.</para>
      </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>The wanda checks engine that orchestrates the execution of configuration checks.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A &postgresql; database for data persistence.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>The RabbitMQ message broker for communicating between the checks engine and the agents.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A &prometheus; instance that retrieves the metrics collected by the &prometheus; node exporter in the registered hosts.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para> The <emphasis role="strong">&t.agent;</emphasis> is a single
      background process (<systemitem>trento agent</systemitem>) running
      on each monitored host of the SAP infrastructure.
    </para>
    <para> See <xref linkend="fig-trento-architecture" /> for additional
      details. </para>
    <figure xml:id="fig-trento-architecture">
      <title>Architectural overview</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="80%"
            fileref="trento-high-level-architecture.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>