<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/usr/share/xml/geekodoc/rng/geekodoc5-flat.rnc"
   type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="sec-housekeeping">
      <title>Housekeeping</title>
     <para>
    When the heartbeat of an agent fails, an option to clean-up the corresponding host will show up both in the
    <guimenu>Hosts</guimenu> overview and the corresponding <guimenu>Host details</guimenu> view.
     </para>
           <figure>
              <title>Clean up button in <guimenu>Hosts</guimenu> overview</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="trento-cleanup-hosts-overview.png"
                    width="70%" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
                 <figure>
              <title>Clean up button in <guimenu>Host details</guimenu> view</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="trento-cleanup-host-details-view.png"
                    width="70%" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
      <para>When the user clicks on the cleanup button, a box will open asking for confirmation.
       If the user grants it, all the components discovered by the agent in that particular host, including the host
       itself and other components that might depend on the ones running on the host, will be removed from the console.
       For example, if the user cleans up the host where the primary application server of an SAP System is registered,
       the entire SAP System will be removed from the console.
      </para>
      <para>Similarly, when a registered application or &hana; instance is no longer discovered, an option to clean it up
       will show up both in the corresponding overview and the corresponding details view.
      </para>
           <figure>
              <title>Clean up button &sap; systems overview</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="trento-cleanup-sap-instance-overview.png"
                    width="70%" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
                 <figure>
              <title>Clean up button in &sap; system details view</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="trento-cleanup-sap-instance-details-view.png"
                    width="70%" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
           <para>When the user clicks the cleanup button, a box will open asking for confirmation.
       If the user grants it, the instance will be removed from the console along with any possible dependencies
       For example, if the user cleans up the ASCS instance of an &sap; system,
       the entire &sap; system will be removed from the console.
      </para>
    </section>