<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/usr/share/xml/geekodoc/rng/geekodoc5-flat.rnc"
   type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
  %entities;
]>

  <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="sec-integration-with-SUSE-Manager">
      <title>Integration with SUSE Multi-Linux Manager</title>
      <para>Trento integrates with SUSE Multi-Linux Manager to provide the &sap; administrator with
      information about relevant patches and upgradable packages for any host
       that is registered with both applications.</para>
      <para>The user must enter the connection settings for SUSE Multi-Linux Manager
       in the <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> view:</para>
     <figure>
         <title>SUSE Multi-Linux Manager settings</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="trento-suse-manager-settings.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
   <para>
   Once the SUSE Multi-Linux Manager settings are configured, the &sap; Basis administrator can test the connection
   by clicking the <guimenu>Test</guimenu> button.
   If the connection is successful, the <guimenu>Host Details</guimenu> view of each host
   managed by SUSE Multi-Linux Manager displays a summary
   of available patches and upgradable packages:</para>
        <figure>
         <title><guimenu>Availale software updates in the Host Details view</guimenu></title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="trento-summary-of-available-software-updates.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
   <para>Click on <guimenu>Relevant Patches</guimenu> to open the <guimenu>Relevant Patches</guimenu> overview containing a list of patches available for that particular host:</para>
           <figure>
         <title><guimenu>Available Patches overview</guimenu></title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="trento-available-patches-overview.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Click <guimenu>Upgradable Packages</guimenu> to open the <guimenu>Upgradable Packages</guimenu> overview containing a list of packages that can be upgraded on that particular host:</para>
           <figure>
         <title><guimenu>Upgradable Packages overview</guimenu></title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="trento-upgradable-packages-overview.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
   <para>By clicking on an advisory or patch link, the user will access the corresponding details view,
    with relevant information about it such us whether it requires a reboot or not, associated
    vulnerabilities, or a list of affected hosts:</para>
            <figure>
         <title><guimenu>Advisory Details view</guimenu></title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="trento-advisory-details-view.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
   <para>There are three types of patches or advisories: security advisories, bug fixes and feature
   enhancements. Security advisories are regarded as critical. If one is avaiable,
   the health of the host will be set to critical. If there are available patches but none of them
    is a security one, the health of the host will switch to warning. When a host cannot be found in
    SUSE Multi-Linux Manager or there is a problem retrieving the data for it, its health is set as unknnown.
   </para>
    <para>
    At any time, the user can clear the SUSE Multi-Linux Manager settings from the Settings view.
    As a result, all information about available software updates disappears from the console and the status of the hosts is adjusted accordingly.</para>
    </section>