<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<article xml:id="container-build-images" xml:lang="en"
 role="concept"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <info>
    <title>Creating custom container images</title>
  </info>
  <para>
    To create a custom image, you need a base image of &sls;. You can use any
    of the pre-built &sls; images.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="sec-download-prebuild-images">
    <title>Pulling base &sls; images</title>
    <para>
      To obtain a pre-built base image, use the following command:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;podman pull registry.suse.com/suse/<replaceable>IMAGENAME</replaceable></screen>
    <para>
      For example, for &sls; 15, the command is as follows:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;podman pull registry.suse.com/suse/sle15</screen>
    <para>
      For information on obtaining specific base images, refer to
      <xref linkend="container-bci-intro"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the container image is ready, you can customize it as described in
      <xref linkend="sec-customize-images"/>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-customize-images">
    <title>Customizing container images</title>
    <section xml:id="sec-customize-repo-registration">
      <title>Repositories and registration</title>
      <para>
        The pre-built images do not have any repositories configured and do not
        include any modules or extensions. They contain a
        <link xlink:href="https://github.com/SUSE/container-suseconnect">zypper
        service</link> that contacts either the SUSE Customer Center or a
        Repository Mirroring Tool (&rmt;) server, according to the
        configuration of the &sls; host that runs the container. The service
        obtains the list of repositories available for the product used by the
        container image. You can also directly declare extensions in your
        <literal>Dockerfile</literal>. For more information, see
        <xref linkend="sec-container-suseconnect"/>.
      </para>
      <note>
        <title>SLE_BCI repository</title>
        <para>
          The default base image includes the SLE_BCI repository. This
          repository is only used when a container is built or runs on a
          non-registered &slsa; host, or when registration credentials are not
          made available to the container. The repository provides a subset of
          &slea; packages useful for customizing &slsa; container images. The
          repository is available without any registration, and it is not
          supported.
        </para>
      </note>
      <para>
        To take advantage of repositories available through your &suse; subscription, build an image so that the secret in the host system is mounted inside the container image. This can be done using the following command:
      </para>
<screen>podman build --no-cache --secret id=SCCcredentials,src=/etc/zypp/credentials.d/SCCcredentials,type=file .</screen>

      <para>
        It is possible to enable additional non-recommended modules via the environment variable <literal>ADDITIONAL_MODULES</literal>, for example:
      </para>
<screen>podman build --env ADDITIONAL_MODULES=sle-module-desktop-applications,sle-module-development-tools</screen>

      <note xml:id="note-build-images-different-codebase">
        <title>Building images on systems registered with &rmt;</title>
        <para>
          When the host system used for building container images is registered
          with &rmt;, the default behavior allows only building containers of
          the same code base as the host. For example, if your container host
          is an &slea; 15 system, you can only build &slea; 15-based images on
          that host by default. To build images for a different &slea; version,
          for example, &slea; 12 on an &slea; 15 host, the host machine
          credentials for the target release can be injected into the container
          as outlined below.
        </para>
        <para>
          Note that if the &rmt; server is using a self-signed certificate, the
          matching CA certificate needs to be added into the container at
          <filename>CA_TRUSTSTORE/rmt-server.pem</filename> for the certificate
          to be accepted.
        </para>
        <para>
          When the host system is registered with SUSE Customer Center, this
          restriction does not apply.
        </para>
      </note>
      <para>
        To obtain the list of repositories, use the following command:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;sudo zypper repos</screen>
      <para>
        This automatically adds all the repositories to the container. For each
        repository added to the system, a new file is created under
        <filename>/etc/zypp/repos.d</filename>. The URLs of these repositories
        include an access token that automatically expires after 12 hours. To
        renew the token, run the command <command>zypper ref -s</command>.
        Including these files in a container image does not pose any security
        risk.
      </para>
      <para>
        To use a different set of credentials, put a custom
        <filename>/etc/zypp/credentials.d/SCCcredentials</filename> file inside
        the container image. It contains the machine credentials that have the
        subscription you want to use. The same applies to the
        <filename>SUSEConnect</filename> file: to override the existing file on
        the host system running the container, add a custom
        <filename>/etc/SUSEConnect</filename> file inside the container image.
      </para>
      <para>
        Now you can create a custom container image by using a
        <filename>Dockerfile</filename> as described in
        <xref linkend="sec-docker-sle-images-customizing-the-images-sles12sp3"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        After you have edited the <filename>Dockerfile</filename>, build the
        image by running the following command in the directory where the
        <filename>Dockerfile</filename> resides:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;podman build .</screen>
      <para>
        For more information about <literal>podman build</literal> options, see
        the
        <link xlink:href="https://docs.podman.io/en/latest/markdown/podman-build.1.html">official
        &podman; documentation</link>.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-docker-sle-images-customizing-the-images-sles12sp3">
      <title>Creating a custom image for &slea; 12 SP5 and later</title>
      <para>
        The following <literal>Dockerfile</literal> creates a simple container
        image based on &sls; 15:
      </para>
<screen>FROM registry.suse.com/suse/sle15
    RUN zypper ref -s &amp;&amp; zypper -n in vim &amp;&amp; zypper -n clean</screen>
      <para>
        When the &podman; host machine is registered with an internal &rmt;
        server, the image requires the SSL certificate used by &rmt;:
      </para>
<screen>FROM registry.suse.com/suse/sle15
    # Import the crt file of our private SMT server
    ADD http://smt./smt.crt /etc/pki/trust/anchors/smt.crt
    RUN update-ca-certificates &amp;&amp; \
        zypper ref -s &amp;&amp; \
        zypper -n in vim &amp;&amp; \
        zypper -n clean</screen>
      <para>
        If you wish to add &slea; extensions and modules to your images, refer
        to <xref linkend="sec-container-suseconnect-modules"/>.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="sec-building-public-cloud">
      <title>Building container images in on-demand &slea; instances in the public cloud</title>
      <para>
        Building container images on &slea; instances that were launched as
        on-demand or pay-as-you-go instances on a public cloud (AWS, GCE or
        Azure) requires additional steps. To install packages and updates, the
        on-demand public cloud instances are connected to the update
        infrastructure. This infrastructure is based on &rmt; servers operated
        by SUSE on public cloud providers.
      </para>
      <para>
        Therefore, your machines need to locate the required services and
        authenticate with them. This can be done using the
        <literal>containerbuild-regionsrv</literal> service. This service is
        available in the public cloud images provided through the marketplaces
        of public cloud providers. Before building an image, this service must
        be started on the public cloud instance by running the following
        command:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;sudo systemctl start containerbuild-regionsrv</screen>
      <para>
        To start it automatically on system boot, enable it:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;sudo systemctl enable containerbuild-regionsrv</screen>
      <para>
        The Zypper plug-ins provided by the &slea; base images connect to this
        service and retrieve authentication details and information about which
        update server to talk to. For this to work, the container has to be
        built with host networking enabled, for example:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;podman build --network host build-directory/</screen>
      <para>
        Since update infrastructure in the public clouds is based upon &rmt;,
        the restrictions on building &slea; images for &slea; versions
        different from the &slea; version of the host apply as well (see
        <xref linkend="note-build-images-different-codebase"/>).
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
