<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<article xml:id="container-basics" xml:lang="en"
 role="concept"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <info>
    <title>Introduction to Linux containers</title>
  </info>
  <para>
    Linux containers offer a lightweight virtualization method to run multiple
    isolated virtual environments simultaneously on a single host. This
    technology is based on the Linux kernel's namespaces for process isolation
    and kernel control groups (cgroups) for resource (CPU, memory, disk I/O,
    network, etc.) management.
  </para>
  <para>
    Unlike &xen; and &kvm;, where a full guest operating system is executed
    through a virtualization layer, Linux containers share and directly use the
    host OS kernel.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Advantages of using containers</term>
      <listitem>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Size</emphasis>: Container images should
              only include the content needed to run an application, whereas a
              virtual machine includes an entire operating system,
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Performance</emphasis>: Containers
              provide near-native performance, as the kernel overhead is lower
              compared to virtualization and emulation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Security</emphasis>: Containers make it
              possible to isolate applications into self-contained units,
              separated from the rest of the host system.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Resources management</emphasis>: It is
              possible to granularly control CPU, memory, disk I/O, network
              interfaces, etc. inside containers (via cgroups).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Flexibility</emphasis>: Container images
              hold all necessary libraries, dependencies, and files needed to
              run an application, thus can be easily developed and deployed on
              multiple hosts.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Limitations of containers</term>
      <listitem>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Containers share the host system's kernel, so the containers have
              to use the specific kernel version provided by the host.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Only Linux-based applications can be containerized on a Linux
              host.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              A container encapsulates binaries for a specific architecture
              (&x86-64; or &aarch64; for instance). So a container made for
              &x86-64; only runs on an &x86-64; system host without the use of
              emulation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Containers in themselves are no more secure than executing
              binaries outside of a container, and the overall security of
              containers depends on the host system. While containerized
              applications can be secured through AppArmor or SELinux profiles,
              container security requires putting in place tools and policies
              that ensure security of the container infrastructure and
              applications.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <section xml:id="sec-concepts-workflow">
    <title>Key concepts and introduction to &podman;</title>
    <para>
      Although &deng; is a popular choice for working with images and
      containers, &podman; provides a drop-in replacement for Docker that
      offers several advantages. While <xref linkend="container-podman"/>
      provides more information on &podman;, this chapter offers a quick
      introduction to key concepts and a basic procedure for creating a
      container image and using &podman; to run a container.
    </para>
    <para>
      The basic &podman; workflow is as follows:
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="container-workflow.png" width="80.0%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>image</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      Running a container, either on a local machine or in a cloud service,
      normally involves the following steps:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Fetch a base image by pulling it from a registry to your local
          machine.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Create a <literal>Dockerfile</literal> and use it to build a custom
          image on top of the base image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Use the created image to start one or more containers.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
      To run a container, you need an image. An image includes all dependencies
      needed to run the application. For example, the &bcia;-Base image
      contains the &slea; distribution with a minimal package selection.
    </para>
    <para>
      While it is possible to create an image from scratch, few applications
      would work in such an empty environment. Thus, using an existing base
      image is more practical in most situations. A base image has no parent,
      meaning it is not based on another image.
    </para>
    <para>
      Although you can use a base image for running containers, the main
      purpose of base images is to serve as foundations for creating custom
      images that can run containers with specific applications, servers,
      services, and so on.
    </para>
    <para>
      Both base and custom images are available through a repository of images
      called a registry. Unless a registry is explicitly specified, &podman;
      pulls images from the
      <link xlink:href="https://registry.opensuse.org">openSUSE</link> and
      <link xlink:href="https://docker.io">Docker Hub</link> registry. While
      you can fetch a base image manually, &podman; can do that automatically
      when building a custom image.
    </para>
    <para>
      To build a custom image, you must create a special file called a
      <filename>Containerfile</filename> or <filename>Dockerfile</filename>
      containing building instructions. For example, a
      <filename>Dockerfile</filename> can contain instructions to update the
      system software, install the desired application, open specific network
      ports, run commands, etc.
    </para>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="container-image-layers.png" width="80.0%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>image</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      You can build images not only from base images, but also on top of custom
      images. So you can have an image consisting of multiple layers. Please
      refer to <xref linkend="container-build-images"/> for more information.
    </para>
  </section>
</article>
